《绿箭》前情回顾
Previously on "Arrow"...
西藏蝮蛇毒
Tibetan pit viper venom.
常用剂量对你来说没用  对吧
A constant dose of that can't be good for you, right?
他会像当初斯莱德那样昏迷
It'll keep him sedated like it did Slade.
没提到伊莎贝尔·罗切夫的死吗
No mention on Isabel Rochev's death?
完全没有
Not a thing.
-杀我吧  杀我吧  -不  不
- Choose. Choose! - No! No!
不  妈  你干什么
No, mom! Mom, what are you doing?
不要杀我的孩子
Both my children will live.
你干什么
What are you doing?!
你拥有真正的勇气
You possess true courage.
不
No!
这件事结束之前  还有一个人
There is still one person who has to die...
必须得死
before this can end.
-不要  -妈
- No... - Mom?!
我庄严宣誓
I do solemnly swear
我会支持
that I will support,
维护和遵守星城宪章
defend, and abide by the Starling City charter.
我会忠诚地
And that I will faithfully
接受星城市长
discharge the duties of the office
办公室的职责
of mayor of Starling City.
我会代表星城居民
That I will tirelessly pursue justice on behalf
不屈不挠地追寻正义
of all of Starling's citizens...
公正无私
impartially,
尽我最大的能力
to the best of my abilities.
愿上帝助我
So help me god.
谢谢
Thank you.
西娅
Thea.
我陪着你呢
I'm here for you.
我知道
I know.
奎恩女士
Ms. Queen.
对你的损失  我深表遗憾
I wanted to offer my sincere condolences on your loss.
你妈妈是个好人
Your mother was a good woman.
她会是个很棒的市长
She would have made a wonderful mayor.
谢谢
Thank you.
我想和奥利弗谈谈
I'd love to speak with Oliver.
如果你看见了他
Well, if you see him,
告诉他  他错过了自己母亲的葬礼
tell him he missed his own mother's funeral.
好几天都没人看见奥利弗了
No one's seen Oliver for a few days.
我们应对悲伤的方式各有不同
We all deal with grief in different ways.
失去母亲简直...
And the loss of a parent is...
它能改变你
Well, it changes you.
你意识到你的祖先现在都指望着你
When you realize that your ancestors now look to you;
继承家族的遗产  延续他们的传奇
That your family's legacy, their continuing works,
全靠你一个人了
are solely in your hands.
如果你看见奥利弗  告诉他我来过了
If you see Oliver, please tell him that I came by.
当然
Of course.
谢谢
Thanks.
我都不知道我为什么要哭
I don't even know why I'm crying.
我都不喜欢莫伊拉
I didn't even like Moira.
别人刚死就这样说她  真是不好
Terrible thing to say about someone after they've just died.
容我辩护一句  她人可不好
In my defense, she was not nice.
她很恶毒
She was diabolical.
这个词在别人的葬礼上不常听到
Not a word you often hear at someone's funeral.
你不是为她哭泣  费利西蒂  而是为奥利弗
U're not crying for her, Felicity, you're crying for Oliver.
他在哪儿
Where is he?
他怎么能不在这里
How could he not be here?
我不知道
I don't know.
如果奥利弗够聪明
If Oliver's smart...
就会跑去他的岛上躲起来
He ran back to his island to hide.
但也许他会出席你们的葬礼
But maybe he'll attend your funerals.
我一直很喜欢这张照片
I always loved this photograph.
我觉得你妈妈看起来特别漂亮
I thought your mother looked particularly beautiful.
她不觉得
Well, she didn't.
她觉得看起来像是暴眼
She thought she looked bug-eyed.
她没说过
She never said.
-你现在怎么样  -很不好
- How are you holding up? - I'm not.
你妈妈为了你付出了生命  西娅
Your mother gave her life for you, Thea.
她向你展示了有多爱你
She showed you how much she loved you in ways
很少有父母能做到这样
very few parents ever could.
我知道
I know.
她死的时候都觉得我恨她
She died thinking I hated her.
但我们需要的只是真相
But all we ever needed was the truth.
杀死她的是一个谎言
It was a lie that killed her.
我不明白
I don't understand.
斯莱德·威尔逊
Slade Wilson.
之前他和奥利弗都在那座小岛上
He was on that island with Oliver.
出于某种原因  他憎恨奥利弗
And despises him for some reason.
我们的生活中有个精神病
There was a psychopath in our lives
而我哥哥从来没警告过我们
and my brother never warned us about him.
西娅  你哥哥爱你胜过自己的生命
Thea, your brother loves you more than life itself.
你该留着那张照片
You should keep that photo.
这个潜水艇有六十多年了
This sub is over 60 years old.
战时这艇搁浅  米拉库鲁就在这艇上
It was carrying the Mirakuru during the war when it ran aground.
有血
Blood.
斯莱德的
Slade's.
他流血过多  即将死去
He was bleeding out, dying.
于是我们决定给他注射米拉库鲁
Until we decided to give him the Mirakuru.
你这主意不怎么样
Not one of your better ideas.
我让你修好潜水艇这个主意怎么样
What about my idea for you to fix this sub?
-你当过海军  -是俄国海军
- You were in the navy. - The Russian navy.
他们教我们如何击沉日本潜水艇  而不是驾驶
They taught us how to sink Japanese sub, not pilot them.
阿纳托利  拜托
Anatoly, please.
我知道机会渺茫  但如果我们能开动潜水艇
I know it's a long shot, but if we get this sub operational,
我们就能击败斯莱德  毁掉米拉库鲁
we can blow Slade and the Mirakuru out of the water
然后离开这座小岛
and get the hell off of this island.
除非你有更好的主意
I mean, unless you have a better idea,
这是我们回家的唯一机会
this is our only chance of getting home.
好吧  我尽量
Ok. I try.
星城警察局
袭击那晚过后  没人见过斯莱德·威尔逊
No one has seen Slade Wilson since the night of the attack.
他没有再威胁奎恩家族
I mean, he hasn't made any further threats on the Queen family,
但我们得找到这个王八...
but we got to find this son of a--
先失陪了
Excuse me. Hey.
追悼会没见到你
Missed you at the reception.
是啊  我得回来
Yeah. I had to get back here,
-看看案子怎么样了  -有线索了吗
- see what was happening with the case. - Any leads?
没有  威尔逊简直是个幽灵
No. Wilson's a ghost.
他不是唯一失踪的人
He's not the only one who's disappeared.
你妹妹有联系过你吗
You heard from your sister?
她只给我发了一条短信  说要换个环境
Nothing apart from a text that she needed a change of scenery.
你还有什么心事吗
Something else on your mind?
是塞巴斯蒂安·布拉德
It's Sebastian Blood.
我觉得有点不对劲
There's something that doesn't seem right.
-劳蕾尔  -爸爸  我知道你在想什么
- Laurel... - Dad, I know what you're thinking.
我指控他杀了他父亲的时候  我太急躁
When I accused him of killing his father, I was upset.
但我有过失误
But just because I had a problem
并不意味着塞巴斯蒂安的事我就错了
doesn't mean I was wrong about Sebastian.
请你不要纠结这事了好吗
Please, don't go down this road again, ok?
怎么又提起这个了
What's bringing this on?
我在追悼会上看到他了
I saw him at the reception.
让我想到他当选市长的唯一原因是
And it struck me that the only reason that he's mayor now
莫伊拉被杀了
is because Moira was killed.
是的  被斯莱德·威尔逊杀的
Yeah, by Slade Wilson.
如果这之间有联系呢
What if there's a connection?
你曾经对我说过
You once told me,
一个警察能做多好取决于直觉
a cop is only as good as his gut.
我是警察的女儿
Well, I'm the daughter of a cop,
我的直觉告诉我
and I know in my gut
塞巴斯蒂安不是你想的那种人
Sebastian is not the man that you think he is.
你确定吗
You sure?
宝贝  上一次
Baby, last time...
我是个醉鬼  你不相信我是对的
I was a drunk. And you were right not to trust me.
但是  爸爸
But, dad...
我现在需要你的信任
I need you to trust me now.
这项法律只是第一步
This legislation is the first step
让星城重拾昨日的光芒
toward making Starling City the jewel that it once was.
再次成为一颗明珠
The jewel that it can be again.
有您的电话  布拉德市长
Phone call for you, Mayor Blood.
我还在适应人们这么叫我  阿莉莎
I'm still getting used to people calling me that, Alyssa.
让对方留言吧
Please take a message.
对方坚持要与您通话
The caller insisted.
他说他是您父亲
He said he's your father.
那不可能
That's impossible.
没关系
Never mind.
我来接
I'll take it.
喂
Hello?
你好啊  塞巴斯蒂安
Hello, Sebastian.
抱歉打搅你
I'm sorry to bother you.
我就是想打个电话来
I just wanted to check in
问问你第一天上任感觉如何
and see how your first day is going.
很好  谢谢你
Very well, thank you.
不过我现在有点忙
But I'm a little busy right now,
如果不介意的话我过一会儿再打给你
So if you'll allow me to call you back,
我会尽快的
I'll do that as soon as I can.
不需要
No need.
我确信你有很多事情要做
I'm sure you have quite a lot of business to attend to.
毕竟你现在是市长了
You are the mayor now, after all.
所以开始工作吧
So get to work.
我们的蛇毒所剩不多了
We're almost out of snake venom.
罗伊这个样子让我想起了巴里
Seeing Roy like this reminds me of Barry.
巴里又让我想起了尖端科技研究实验室
And Barry reminds me of S.T.A.R. Labs.
尖端科技研究实验室让我想起了
S.T.A.R. Labs reminds me
他们正在研究的米拉库鲁的解药
of the Mirakuru cure that they're working on,
要是我们现在能用上多好呀
which we could really use...right now.
是啊  特别是因为伊莎贝尔·罗切夫
Yeah, especially since Isabel Rochev
肯定被人注射了那玩意
was clearly injected with the stuff.
你怎么知道
How do you know?
因为除此之外
'cause there's no other way
她不可能被九毫米中空弹毙命后
she could be walking around after being shot dead-on
还能到处跑
with a nine-millimeter hollow point.
我给奥利弗留了一大堆关于
I've left about a dozen messages for Oliver
伊莎贝尔·罗切夫回归的语音留言  但毫无回应
about Isabel being back. No response.
你找到他的线索了吗
You have any luck finding him?
很多  但全是坏消息
Tons. All of it bad.
总之是他的护照  手机
There's been no activity on his passport, cell phone,
银行账户  还有其他东西全都没有活动
or bank accounts-- what's left of them, anyhow.
星城第一银行
面部识别也未能在任何机场
And facial recognition hasn't spotted him in any airport,
公交或火车站发现他
bus, or train station.
好吧
Right.
莎拉呢
What about Sara?
一样毫无踪迹
Nothing either.
狄格  一般来讲人们不会消失得这么彻底
Dig, people don't just go missing like this,
除非
unless...
别那么想  费利西蒂
Don't go there, Felicity.
如果她真是那样了呢
What if she is?
如果奥利弗那样了呢
What if Oliver is?
也许我们找不到他的原因是
Maybe the reason we can't find him is because--
他还活着  费利西蒂
He's alive, Felicity.
如果他死了  伊莎贝尔·罗切夫肯定
If he wasn't, Isabel Rochev wouldn't be so shy
会毫不遮掩地告诉我们  相信我  他还活着
about rubbing it in our faces. Believe me, he's alive.
我希望你有其他办法找到他
Well, I hope you have some way on how to find him,
因为我已经竭尽所能了
because I am running out of places to look and people to ask.
我知道该去找谁
I know who to ask.
谢谢你同意见我们
Thanks for agreeing to see us.
狄格尔先生
Mr. Diggle.
我以为上次碰面的时候已经说得很清楚
Thought I made it clear after our last meeting.
超能力联合调查组不再对你提供帮助了
As far as A.R.G.U.S. is concerned, you're out of favors.
我不是为我自己的事  阿曼达
I'm not asking for myself, Amanda.
我是为星城的每一个人
I'm asking for everyone in Starling City.
我需要你们找到奥利弗·奎恩
I need you to find Oliver Queen.
狄格
Dig.
那台计算机用的是XK-15型处理器
That computer's running an XK-15 processor.
费利西蒂
Felicity...
那个东西应该还不存在才对
But that's not even supposed to exist yet.
我想要一个
I want one.
告诉我你找到了什么
Let me know what you find.
我没时间找你的朋友  狄格尔先生
I don't have time to keep track of your friends, Mr. Diggle.
我们在处理更紧急的事
We deal with more pressing issues here.
你不明白  奥利弗失踪了
You don't understand. Oliver's disappeared.
也许他只是需要点时间
Maybe he needs some time.
也许你们两人
Or is it possible that the two of you
只是没有找对地方
simply haven't been looking in the right place?
你们试过面部识别了吗
Did you try facial recognition?
当然了  做过三遍了
Yes, I ran it three times.
阿曼达  拜托了
Amanda, please.
斯莱德·威尔逊有一支
Slade Wilson has an army
强大军队个个跟他一样
of men just like him.
有多少人曾经注射过米拉库鲁
How many men have been exposed to the Mirakuru?
足够彻底破坏这座城市了
Enough to lay waste to this city.
我们现在就需要找到奥利弗
We need to find Oliver right now.
我会尽力的
I'll see what I can do.
威登酒吧
-莎拉联系过你吗  -没有
- Have you heard from Sara? - No.
-你能打电话问下曼蒂能不能看店吗  -好的
- Can you just call Mandy and see if she'll cover our bar?  - Okay.
伊莎贝尔·罗切夫
Isabel Rochev.
我知道你是谁
I know who you are.
我能为你做什么  罗切夫小姐
What can I do for you, Ms. Rochev?
请节哀顺变  西娅
I'm sorry for your loss, Thea.
你来就是为了这个吗
Is that why you came here?
向我表示哀悼
Offer me your condolences?
对  哀悼  还有这个
My condolences, and to give you this.
是让你腾出酒吧的通知
It's a notice to vacate the premises.
这个酒吧还有它所位于的钢铁厂
This club and the steel factory in which its located
都是奎恩联合企业的财产
are all assets of Queen Consolidated.
-不  你不能这样  -事已成定局
- No, you--you can't do this. - It's already done.
我还有多长时间
How long do I have?
两天
A couple days.
泰森议员想邀请你吃晚饭
Councilman Tyson is asking about dinner.
我今晚有安排了
I already have plans tonight.
不好意思  我不是故意要闯进来的
Hi. Excuse me, I didn't mean to barge in.
只是前台没人  所以
It's just that nobody was at your front desk, so...
劳蕾尔  没事  请进
Laurel, of course, please come in.
你先出去吧
Give us a moment.
两天里见到你两次
Twice in two days.
我怎有如此荣幸
To what do I owe the pleasure?
我倒是希望是有好事
I wish I could say that this was pleasure,
但是有个案子要你帮忙
but it's about a case.
我刚上任  就开始有人找我帮忙了
I've barely moved in and people are already asking me for favors.
我现在真是市长了啊
I guess I really have arrived.
的确如此
You certainly have.
说吧  我能帮你什么忙
So tell me, how can I help you?
墨菲和邓利维的案件
Murphy vs. Dunleavy.
政府指控一家房地产开发商
The state's charged a real estate developer
说他们以所谓的"道德问题"为理由
for turning away low-income tenants
拒绝低收入的租客
based on his so-called "Morality."
你坐吧  我猜啊
Have a seat. Let me guess.
我们亲爱的公平租赁政策的长官
Our dear fair housing commissioner
不愿意出庭当你的专家证人
isn't willing to testify as your expert witness.
没错  而且前任市长也不打算对他施压
Exactly. And your predecessor wasn't willing to lean on him.
那么你很幸运  因为我跟他不一样
Well, lucky for you, I'm not my predecessor.
知道吗  这事让我想起了以前
You know, this actually reminds me of one I had
我当社区组织者时接的一个案子
during my days as a community organizer.
我正希望如此
I was hoping that it would.
我在创新联合会见过很多这样的案件
I've seen dozens of cases like this at CNRI.
我们都记得自己的出身  这是好事
Well, it's a good thing we both remember where we came from.
我很乐意帮你
I'm happy to help.
谢谢
Thank you.
劳蕾尔
Laurel...
你能回地检办工作  我真的很高兴
I'm really glad you got your job back at the DA's office.
我很期待我们能长久一起共事
I look forward to us working together for a long time.
我也是
As do I.
有用吗
Is it working?
我们马上就要远程访问那台电脑了
We're about to remote access the computer right now.
老实说  如果你哪天律师当腻了
I'll tell you this, if you ever get tired of practicing law,
去当间谍一定很成功
you'd make a pretty decent spy.
这事经过批准了对吧
You guys have a warrant for this, right?
你就...
Just...
好极了
Terrific.
至少告诉我这是黑了谁的电脑吧
Could you at least tell me who's computer you bugged?
星城  市长办公室
你们开什么玩笑  我还给他投过票呢
You're kidding. I voted for him.
我要知道
I need to know
布拉德有什么见不得光的文件资料
if there's anything incriminating in Blood's files.
我不管了  反正这工作也没什么前途
What the hell, this is a dead end job, anyway.
看上去都没问题
This all looks pretty benign.
很多政策性文件
Lots of policy papers,
从他竞选办公室转过来的旧文件
old documents transferred from his campaign office.
新闻发布稿
Draft press releases...
等等  刚才那张
Wait, wait, wait, click back.
立即发布  "发生了这种悲剧
"For immediate release-- my thoughts and prayers
我在此为奎恩家族
are with the Queen family in the aftermath
诚心默哀祈祷"
of this unspeakable tragedy.
他就是在莫伊拉死后写了新闻发言稿呗
So he worked up a press release after Moira was killed.
不  不是的
No, he didn't.
他是在莫伊拉死前写好的
He wrote that the day before Moira died.
她说的没错  看这个落款的时间
She's right. Look at the timestamp.
2014年4月23日  上午8:16
天哪
Oh, my God.
塞巴斯蒂安早就知道斯莱德会杀她
Sebastian knew Slade was going to kill her.
这是TX50卫星频率通讯机吗
Is that the satellite frequency communicator TX50?
我可以摸一下吗
Can I touch it?
我承认这有点怪有点诡异
I know that sounds a little weird and creepy,
但是我现实生活里从来没见过这个
but I've never seen one in real life.
这是机密设备  斯莫克小姐
It's classified equipment, Ms. Smoak.
你一定觉得很有权威
You must feel very powerful...
知道每个人的每件事
knowing everything about everyone.
不是像斯大林那种邪恶独裁者那样
Not powerful in an evil dictator Stalin way.
更像是"知识就是力量"那样
More of a... knowledge is power, way.
长官  有情况
Ma'am. We have something.
我早该想到
I should have known.
怎样
What?
奥利弗在他部署行动的那个藏身处
Oliver's at the lair from which he conducts his operations.
但我们刚从那过来啊
But we were just there.
不是那个地方
Not that lair.
他另一个藏身之所
His other one.
就像骑自行车一样
Like riding bicycle.
只不过在水下骑
Underwater.
那是什么声音
What's that sound?
我们被卡住了
We're stuck.
正如当时的日本人那样
Like Japanese were.
潜水艇都有鱼雷的吧
Submarines have torpedoes, right?
我们能炸开一条路出去吗
Can we blast our way out?
我现在明白为什么说你们俩天生一对了
I can see why you two are made for each other.
你喜欢用爆炸解决问题
You like your explosions.
好  鱼雷
Yes, torpedoes
我去[俄语]
Chert voz'mi.
你说什么
What?
这些是回转鱼雷
These are kaiten torpedoes.
是人工操作的
Manually operated.
得有人从里面控制鱼雷
Someone needs to steer from inside.
那控制的人怎么躲开鱼雷的爆炸
Okay, but then, how do they get away from the explosion?
没法躲开
They do not.
-你们怎么找到我的  -沃勒说的
- How did you find me? - Waller.
我们都很担心你
We were worried about you.
你连你妈的葬礼都没参加
After you missed your mother's funeral.
抱歉我没有去
I'm sorry that I didn't go.
我当时去墓地了
I left for the cemetery.
可最后却到这里了
But I ended up here.
这里是...
Here is...
这里是防止钢铁厂那边出问题
Here was a secondary facility
才建造的备用设施
in case the foundry was compromised.
但却变成了一个我可以...
But it became somewhere that I could just go and...
独自待着的地方
be alone.
她因我而死
She's dead because of me.
五年前
Five years ago...
我本可以治好斯莱德
I could have cured Slade.
如果那样  这一切都不会发生
And that would have prevented all of this.
而现在
And now,
剩下这些所有我关心的人
all the people left that I care about,
我们都成了他的猎物
we are all in his crosshairs.
今晚一切都将结束
It ends tonight.
怎么结束
How?
我把自己交给斯莱德
I turn myself over to Slade.
我要终结这场仇杀
I end this vendetta.
奥利弗  你以为把自己交给他
Oliver, you think this ends
这一切就会结束了吗
with you turning yourself over to Slade?
是的
Yes, I do.
她死了之后
After she was gone...
他告诉我必须再死一个人
he told me that one more person had to die.
然后就结束了
And then it would end.
斯莱德杀了我就结束了
This ends for Slade when he kills me.
我不接受
I don't accept that.
你也不应该接受
You shouldn't, either.
你不能这么逆来顺受  奥利弗
You can't just accept things, Oliver.
如果我接受了自己的命运
If I had accepted my life,
就会像我母亲一样成为赌城的鸡尾酒女郎
I would be a cocktail waitress in Vegas like my mother,
我永远也不会去上大学
and I never would have gone to college,
永远也不会跑到千里之外
and I never would have moved a thousand miles away
在奎恩联合企业工作
to work at Queen Consolidated,
永远也不会相信一个兜帽疯子的话
and I never would have believed some crazy guy in a hood
他说我不仅仅能做一个技术女
when he told me I could be more than just some IT girl.
求你了  不要这样做
Please don't do this.
费利西蒂
Felicity...
有人曾经跟我说过
Someone once told me
英雄主义的本质就是为他人牺牲
that the essence of heroism is to die so others can live.
没那么简单  奥利弗
It's not that simple, Oliver.
就这么简单
Yes, it is.
斯莱德的整个计划
Slade's whole plan
就是要夺走我的一切
was to take everything from me.
他做到了
He did.
他赢了
He wins.
现在只要我死  就都结束了
All that's left is for me to die.
不  一定还有别的方法
No, there has to be another way.
没有了
There isn't.
西娅  拜托  我明白你很难过
Thea, please. I understand you're upset.
现在我们全都有点情绪化
This is an emotional time for all of us.
我不是闹情绪
I'm not being emotional.
我...我成了孤儿
I'm...I'm an orphan!
我是个没有工作没有家的孤儿
I'm a jobless and homeless orphan.
我在这儿什么都没有了
There's nothing left for me here.
我还在这里
I'm here.
谢谢你  但是
I thank you for that, but...
说实话  我需要重新开始
Honestly, I need to start over.
奥利弗
Oliver.
你没去参加葬礼
We missed you at the funeral.
也没参加追悼会
And the reception.
很抱歉我没有出席
I'm sorry that I couldn't be there.
这里出什么事了
What's going on here?
西娅在考虑要离开星城
Thea's thinking of leaving Starling City.
不是在考虑  我决定了
No, I am leaving.
沃尔特  能让我跟我妹妹聊几句吗
Walter, could I speak to my sister for a moment?
我相信你运气更好
I'm sure you'll have better luck.
奥利  拜托  别想要说服我留下来
Ollie, please. Just don't even try to convince me to stay.
我不会的  我觉得离开是个好主意
I won't. I think it's a good idea.
你应该尽可能远离星城
You should get as far from Starling City as you possibly can.
我们一家人
In our family,
在你  我  妈妈还有爸爸之间
out of you, me, mom and dad,
你是最好的那个
you are the best of us.
你的心灵最纯洁
You have the purest heart.
我不能让你失去那份纯洁
And I can't ever have you lose that.
好吗
OK?
答应我
You promise me?
好
OK.
我知道自己并非一直都是好哥哥
I know that I haven't always been the best brother,
或是朋友  或是别的什么你所期望的
or friend, or whatever you've needed me to be.
但是自从你出生以来的每一天
But there has not been a day since you were born
我都因为有你这样一个妹妹而倍感珍惜
where I didn't cherish having you as a sister.
我...
I'll, um,
等我安顿下来会联系你的
get in touch when I get settled somewhere.
呼叫伊莎贝尔
我是奥利弗
It's Oliver.
现在结束一切吧
This ends now.
我会一个人去码头
I'll be at the pier, I'll be alone.
我去
I'll do it.
彼得  你会死的
Peter, you'll die.
我已经死了
I'm already dead.
辐射中毒
Radiation poisoning.
艾沃的小礼物
Ivo's little gift.
他说他想知道米拉库鲁是不是能治愈癌症
He said he needed to find out if Mirakuru could cure cancer.
估计我们永远也不会知道了
Guess we'll never find out.
抱歉  彼得  我不知道
Oh, I'm sorry, Peter, I didn't know.
艾沃说英雄主义的本质就是为他人牺牲
Ivo said the essence of heroism is to die so that others can live.
我一直坚信这一点
I held on to that.
这是唯一能给我希望的事
It's the only thing that gave me hope.
所以我决定去
So I'll go.
也许我无法拯救数百万的性命
I mean, I may not be saving millions of lives,
但我能救你们
but I'll be saving yours.
这就是一切开始的地方
This is where it all started.
我就在那里登上了"金牌奎恩"
Got on the "Queen's Gambit" right over there.
我应该死在那艘船上
I should have died on that boat.
如果我死了  这一切都不会发生
If I had, none of this would have happened.
我永远也不会遇到你
I never would have met you.
莎朵和我母亲还会活着
Shado and my mother would still be alive.
其他人也不会因为我而死
No one else is going to die because of me.
狄格尔  搞什么鬼
Diggle, what the hell?
斯莱德·威尔逊
Slade Wilson.
他把你的身份告诉我了
He told me who you were.
他伤害你了吗
Did he hurt you?
没有
No.
他想伤害你
He was trying to hurt you.
你失踪之后
And when you went missing,
我就联系了
I reached out...
你的搭档们
to your partners.
他们告诉了我你的打算
They told me what you were planning on doing.
我必须那么做
It's what I have to do.
能让我们单独谈会儿吗
Will you give us a moment?
那个计划实施的那天晚上
You thought about telling me...
你就想告诉我
the night of the undertaking.
几乎每天晚上我都想告诉你
I thought about telling you almost every night.
那你为什么不说
Why didn't you?
汤米知道
Tommy knew.
对吗
Didn't he?
你当时和他在一起
You were with him.
他临死时你陪着他
You were with him at the end.
他最后的话都是在挂念你
His last words were about you.
他想知道你是否安全
He wanted to know if you were safe.
抱歉我没能救下他
Sorry I couldn't save him.
还有我母亲
And my mother.
但我还能救你
But I can save you.
还能救西娅
And Thea.
只要我今晚了结这一切  我还能救下星城
I can save the city if this ends tonight.
不对
No.
你不能
No!
你不能白白送死  奥利
You can't commit suicide, Ollie.
你不能对我这么做
You won't do that to me.
还有莎拉  还有你的朋友们
Or to Sara, or to your friends.
还有西娅  奥利弗
Or to Thea. Oliver...
她刚刚失去母亲
She just lost her mother.
再失去你就会彻底毁了她
Losing you would destroy her.
但她至少能活着
But she'll be alive.
我对兜帽或者面具或者人造武器
I don't know anything about hoods and masks or human weapons
或这里的一切并不了解
or any of this.
但我了解你
But I know you.
我就像熟知自己的名字那样了解你
I know you like I know my own name.
鉴于你的种种秘密  我知道这么想很疯狂
And I realize it may sound crazy in light of your secret,
但我对你的为人和品行了如指掌  奥利弗
but I know who you are in your bones, Oliver.
而我认识的这个人
And that person--
这个人从不轻言放弃
That person doesn't give up.
这个人总能另辟蹊径
That person, he always finds a way.
这次不行了
Not this time.
你错了
You're wrong.
你想保护你深爱的人吗
You want to protect the people who you love?
那你就必须阻止斯莱德·威尔逊
Then the only way to do that is to stop Slade Wilson.
-劳蕾尔  我做不到  -你当然能
- Laurel, I can't! - Yes, you can!
你需要阻止塞巴斯蒂安·布拉德  因为他
By stopping Sebastian Blood, because Sebastian
正在和斯莱德·威尔逊合谋
is working with Slade Wilson.
我有证据
I have proof.
斯莱德·威尔逊杀死你的母亲
Slade Wilson killed your mother
就是为了把塞巴斯蒂安推上市长大位
so that Sebastian could become mayor.
你之前说的他的事全是对的
You were right about him.
戴骷髅面具的人为斯莱德·威尔逊工作
The man in the skull mask works for Slade Wilson.
而一直以来
And this entire time,
这个人就是塞巴斯蒂安
it was Sebastian.
当下的情势
What's happening
已经远超你和斯莱德的私怨了
is bigger than you and Slade.
星城需要绿箭
This city needs the Arrow.
这是做什么
What's this for?
我希望你能避一避
I don't want you to be in here.
-不  我要和你在一起  -莎拉
- No, I'm going to stay with you-- - Sara.
如果计划失败了
If this doesn't work,
我要确保你的安全
I need you to be safe.
事成之后我们就去找你
We will come for you when it's over.
那好
Ok.
你弄清楚怎么发射鱼雷了吗
Do you know how the torpedo works?
我爬进去  他发射  我操纵  你祈祷
I get in, he fires, I steer, you pray.
彼得  你的这种行为实在是
Peter, what you're doing is...
看清现实而已
Practical.
我已经寿命将尽
My time's already up.
我想说勇敢
Brave.
你必须知道这点
You need to know that.
我觉得我就没法像你这样牺牲自我
And I don't think that I could do something like this.
你已经做到了  看看你为我们做的种种
You have. What you did for us--
杀回船上  救出我们
coming back to that boat, setting us free?
我回到船上是因为我想回家
I came back to the boat because I want to go home.
我本无意拯救任何人
I wasn't thinking about saving anybody.
我  我不是这样的人
It's...it's not who I am.
或许现在还不是
Maybe not yet.
-发射吗  -莎拉安全了吗
- Launch? - Is Sara clear?
-安全了  -那就动手
- Yes. - Yes.
-您好  -幸会
- Hello. - Good to see you.
克林顿  你在车里等我吧
Clinton. You can wait in the car.
您确定这样没问题吗
Are you sure that's a good idea?
我不会有事的
Nothing's going to happen to me here.
您好啊  市长先生
How are you doing, mr. Mayor?
您好  幸会  很高兴见到您
Hi. Good to see you, good to see you.
-您好  谢谢  -谢谢
- Hey, thank you. - Thank you.
-您好  -很荣幸见到您  市长
- Hi. - Good to see you, Sir.
恭喜您  布拉德市长
Congratulations, Mayor Blood.
幸会幸会
Nice to see you.
塞巴斯蒂安  能一起吃顿饭吗
Sebastian, may I join you for dinner?
麻烦等一下
Hey, can you hold that?
太感谢了  哥们  太感谢了
Oh, thanks a lot, man, appreciate it.
克林顿·霍格
Clinton Hogue.
我有些问题要问你
I have some questions for you.
去死吧你们
Go to hell.
你确定要这么硬撑着吗
You sure that's how you want to play it?
你以为我之前没挨过打吗
You think I've never took a beating before?
老兄  到最后你会宁可挨打
Pal, you're going to wish I beat you.
我来审问你
I'll be your interrogator.
-逗我呢  -克林顿·霍格
- Is this a joke? - Clinton Hogue.
社会保障号码为306003894
Social security number 306003894.
你们想干什么
What the hell's this supposed to be?
瞧瞧
Oh, look at this.
你在开曼群岛还有个银行账户呢
You have a bank account in the Cayman Islands.
两百万  小金库挺充实啊
$2 million, quite the little nest egg.
但是  貌似你刚刚
But...looks like you just
进行了一笔转账
approved a wire transfer of
把一百万电汇进星城的一家慈善机构了
$1 million to a charity here in Starling City.
真是慷慨啊
Very generous.
剩下的该怎么办呢
What should I do with the rest?
-绿色和平[环保组织]  -好主意
- Greenpeace. - Great cause!
他们非常感谢你的倾囊相助
And they really appreciate the support.
你个婊子
You bitch!
能上无线网的婊子
Bitch with wifi.
克林顿  看来你父母的
Hey, Clinton, looks like your mom and dad have
退休金投资收益颇丰啊
a really nice retirement portfolio, too,
但是糟了  他们马上
but they, oh, no, are just
就要做一笔血赔的投资了
about to make some really bad investments.
慢着  别  停下
Ok, wait, just wait--just--stop!
你们想知道什么
What do you want to know?
我在你母亲的追悼会上没见着你
I missed you at your mother's memorial service.
我本想当面表达哀悼之情的
I wanted to offer my condolences.
你当上市长了
You're the mayor.
恭喜了
Congratulations.
这是你奋斗多年的梦想
You've always wanted that.
相信我奥利弗  我更希望换种方式上任
Believe me, Oliver, I wish it had happened a different way.
令堂和我  我们政见相差甚远
Your mother and I, we--we didn't agree on much.
但我们都是为星城着想
But we both wanted what was best for Starling City.
我会帮这座城市重寻希望  我向你保证
I will help this city find its heart again, I promise you that.
你真觉得他...
Do you really think that he...
会让你这么做吗
will let that happen?
斯莱德·威尔逊
Slade Wilson.
你怎么知道我跟斯莱德·威尔逊的事
How do you know I've been working with Slade Wilson?
因为我就是绿箭
Because I'm the Arrow.
怪不得啊
Of course.
现在我都明白了
It all makes sense now.
绿箭原来就在我身边
It was right in front of me.
你到我办公室跟我握手
You came to my office and you shook my hand.
你说我们一起拯救星城
You said that together, we can save this city.
你觉得你释放斯莱德的米拉库鲁大军后
You think that there will be a city to be saved
还有城市可以拯救吗
after you unleash Slade's Mirakuru army?
他们导致的损失  只是让星城做好准备
They'll only cause enough damage to make the city ready.
准备接受你的领导吗
Ready for your leadership?
准备实现我对这个城市的远大期望
For my vision of what this city could be.
变成更好的城市
A better city.
经历过暴风雨般的洗礼之后
And after the storm they're about to suffer,
星城人民
the people of Starling
会支持并跟随我去建造那座城市
will support and follow me to that city.
斯莱德承诺你的绝对不会兑现
Whatever Slade promised you, he will not deliver.
他只是想伤害我
He wants to hurt me.
你只是一盘更大的棋局里的棋子
You are a pawn in a much larger game.
斯莱德承诺让我当市长
Slade promised me city hall.
他兑现了这个承诺
And he delivered.
他挺言而有信的
He makes good on his promises.
我知道他也向你作出过承诺
I understand he made you a promise, too.
你想干什么
What are you going to do?
你想在大庭广众的餐厅里
You going to stab the mayor
刺杀市长吗
in a restaurant full of people?
星城的历史翻开了新篇章  奥利弗
It's a new day in Starling City, Oliver.
无论你做什么  都无法阻挡历史的脚步
And there's nothing you can do to stop it.
沃尔特来电
沃尔特来电  拒绝接听
斯莱德的人今晚要发起进攻
Slade's men are taking the city tonight.
-让他们试试吧  -人数比我们想象的要多
- They can try. - There's more men than we thought,
都服用了米拉库鲁  可能是场屠杀
all on Mirakuru. It could be a massacre.
除非我们先下手为强
Not if we get to them first.
无论如何  我们按原定计划行事
We stick to the plan, no matter what.
斯莱德会利用下水道系统
Slade's using the sewer system.
你们可以从洛克街过去  然后往东南走
You can drop in at Rock Avenue and then head southeast.
管线汇集处在沃特街
The lines converge at Water Street.
如果斯莱德的大军在地下  他可能就在那里
If Slade's army's underground, that's probably where he'll be.
好  我们走  狄格尔  准备好了吗
Good. Let's go. Diggle, you ready?
那是当然
Never not.
我也要一起去
I'm coming, too.
不行
No, you're not.
费利西蒂可以把消息给我
Felicity can give me a radio.
我可以时刻告诉你们最新情况
I'll just be your eyes and your ears.
我不会碍事的  我保证
I'll stay out of your way, I promise.
-我不会有事的  -万一出事了呢
- Nothing will happen to me. - What if it did?
斯莱德的人个个都能力强大  几乎无法阻止
Slade's men, one on one, they are nearly impossible to stop.
我需要你相信我
I need you to trust me.
我需要你好好的
And I need you to be safe.
那他们两个呢
But not them?
这件事开始就是我们三个人一起做的
This started with the three of us.
是时候回到最初的阵容了
It's time we got back to that.
今晚我们齐心协力
Tonight we rise up as one
夺回这座城市
and take back this city.
我看到布拉德的大军了
I have eyes on Blood's army.
收到  我马上把
Got it. I'm forwarding dig your ping
他们上面街道的设计图转发到你手机上
along with the foundation schematics of the topside avenue.
按照我给你画出的路线走
Follow the route I laid out on the blueprints.
你就会看到结构内部的接合点了
You'll see structural joints in the concrete.
下载中
已完成
都炸掉  布拉德就葬身地下了
Blow them all and Blood gets buried.
明白
Got it.
今天股市以400点开市
The market opened today at 400 points
部分原因是奎恩联合企业的突然奋起
thanks in part to the surprise rally of Queen's Consolidated.
尽管最近发生了悲剧  但是新领导班子
New leadership has investers excited about
让投资者对公司的前景大为看好
...the company's future in spite of this recent tragedy.
请问一下  为什么现在还不能上车
Um, excuse me, why can't I board my train?
抱歉  女士  现在是商务座旅客上车时间
I'm sorry, ma'am, it's just business class right now.
普座稍后就可以了
Coach will be boarding soon.
好吧
OK.
过来  伙计
Come on, pal.
那不是铁山监狱的逃犯吗
Isn't that one of the Iron Heights escapees?
这个笨蛋想去抢便利店
Dumbass here tried to rob a convenience store
不过我过去他就束手就擒了
but gave up as soon as I pulled in.
我可以暂时把他留在这里吗
Mind if I just stick him here for a minute?
没问题
No, go ahead.
我跟你说
I'm just asking here.
奥利弗  你一直那么努力去避免再杀人
Oliver, you've worked really hard not to kill anymore.
把整个街区炸毁埋了那些人无异于谋杀
Dropping an entire block on these guys is murder.
至少是屠杀
Manslaughter, at least.
他们不是人
They're not men.
再也不是了
Not anymore.
狄格尔一准备好就让他引爆炸药
Have Diggle blow the charges the moment he's ready.
奥利弗
Oliver?
我们将带领这座城市走出黑暗
We will lead this city out of the darkness,
你们都将助我一臂之力
and each one of you will help me.
走
Come on.
奥利弗  你到底在哪里
Oliver, where the hell are you?!
你杀了我...
You killed me...
那就礼尚往来吧
Let me return the favor.
现在几点了
You got the time?
九点
It's, uh, 9:00.
谢了
Thanks.
奥利弗  快出现
Oliver, please.
星级实验室来电
西斯科  现在真不是时候
Cisco, now is really not a good time.
那边
There.
奥利
Ollie!
他们人太多了
There's too many of them!
我们打不过
We can't fight.
我们不跟他们打
We're not going to.
转舵
Turn the wheel!
往哪个方向
What direction?
无所谓  快转舵
It does not matter. Just turn the wheel.
-转不动  -必须转
- I can't! - That is not an option.
好了
I got it!
天呐  动了
My God. We're moving!
好  太棒了
Good, good.
莎拉  成功了
Sara, we did it.
莎拉
Sara!
奥利弗
Oliver!